短假期是个疯狂的念头
The mini break is a colossal cauldron of crazy,
把人急得像热锅上的蚂蚁
within which boils a bewildering broth of baffle.
你不知道能否有条不紊地
How the cust can you be certain your condensed campaign
完成紧张的旅行和购物计划
and consumption is proceeding correctly?
别担心 因为乱炖魔王 理查德·阿尤阿德
Fear not for I the heinous hodge podge called Richard Ayoade,
会帮你把慌乱的旅行变得紧凑有序
am here to get your short hall game tight!
我将和制作组请得起的那些名人一起
I, joined by some of the most available and affordable names in light ent,
带你领略最多姿多彩的短假期
am going to rollick you round a maxi-packed mini-break.
这是场简单粗暴的旅行
This is travel without mercy.
今晚开始的四十八小时旅行
Tonight 48 hours in the city
来到了至少要两天建成的城市
which took at least two days to build;
罗马
I’m talking R to the ome.
每年有超过两千万的游客涌进这里
Over 20 mill tourists per annum swamp the eternal city
领略这里无与伦比的历史文化
to enjoy a peerless phalanx of the ancient.
干杯
Cheers
本期我们请来了演员兼编剧 喜剧明星
And, in this ep, the dolce to my vita is played by male actor,
马特·卢卡斯和我一起享受美好时光
writer, and comedian, Matt Lucas.
我觉着 我的智商至少比熊高
I could outwit a racoon- I reckon.
我们将一起
Together we will-
像巨人一样战斗
Clash like titans:
我们仿佛坐时光机来到了古罗马
It’s like stepping out the tardis into actual ancient Rome.
像凤头鸟一样吃东西
Chew like cardinals-
你喜欢微芯片吗
You like micro chips.
不然我是怎么成名的
What do you think built this temple?
像公爵一样开车
And drive like dukes-
我在罗马看的最多的就是我发白的指节
The thing that I see most in Rome, are my own whitening knuckles.
我们来啦 但是这趟值吗
We’re here! But should we have come?
值得
Yes.
你好像慢了半拍吧
Is that the delay I’m going to be dealing with?
值得
Yes.
假如想要省钱 游客来罗马玩两天只需一人花185英镑
Frugal forward planners could snatch 48 hours in Rome for £185pp.
但这趟出租车
This cab trip has played a key part in already
足以破坏整个省钱计划
making that target a massive impossibility.
您真绅士
You are a gentleman.
非常感谢
Thank you very much.
他好像对小费很不满意
He looked at that like it was half of what he expected.
这温度你受得了吗
How are you with the heat?
不太行 你呢
Not great, you?
我显然也受不住
I’m you know, terrible, obviously.
好了 这下我们意见统一了
Great we’re in the right place then.
当然
Course we are.
说到这 我们为什么要来罗马
Actually come to think of it, why have we come to Rome?
让我告诉你
I’ll tell you why:
罗马帝国由著名的弑兄者罗慕路斯于公元前753年建立
Founded by noted brother slayer, Romulus, in 753BC,
在公元476年之前 罗马一直是罗马帝国的首都
Rome was the HQ of the Roman Empire until 476AD.
如果你喜欢历史的话 那你真是来对地方了
If you like old shizz you’ve hit the melon farming mother load.
著名的罗马人有 军事扩张者尤利乌斯·凯撒
Famous Romans include serial expansionist Julius Caesar,
荧屏女神索菲亚·罗兰  还有我心中的大师费德里科·费里尼
screen siren Sofia Loren and my personal maestro, Federico Fellini.
罗马的许多设计都对球形情有独钟
Many Roman inventions have enjoyed a near globular grip:
无论是水泥 拱门
I’m talking concrete, I’m talking the arch,
渡槽 下水道或是书籍
I’m talking the aqueduct, I’m talking sewers, I’m talking books
甚至是公共厕所的基石 都是如此
and I’m talking the bed rock of any civilised society- public toilets y’all.
今晚我们将入住G罗浮旅馆
This eve we will kip down at the G Rough,
一个只有十个房间的精品酒店 由十六世纪的住宅改造而成
a 10 room boutique hotel hewn from a 16th century townhouse.
-你好啊  -我叫马蒂奥
- Hello guys how are you doing? - My name is Mateo.
欢迎来到G罗浮旅馆
Welcome to G-Rough.
要我帮您拿行李吗
So do you mind if I look after your luggage?
好的 请
Please go, go.
只是为了称下衣服有多重
The scales are just to weigh my clothes.
每间房间都致敬了一位意大利设计师
Each room is homage to an Italian designer
每位设计师的名字都被写在了酒店里
with whom the hotel is on figurative first name terms.
他为什么要吸一颗蛋
Why is he trying to smoke an egg?
“罗浮”指的是这里粗糙的墙壁 好在华丽的饰品
The ‘rough’ refs the bare plaster walls which are offset by blingy biz
和高档家具帮它美化了不少
and furniture that probably isn’t self-assemble.
完工后一定更棒
Yeah it’ll be even better when it’s finished.
顺着楼梯上去就是露台了
This cripplingly chic combo is topped off with a roof terrace
矮得连烟屁股都会露出来
that isn’t even covered in fag butts!
你干什么呢
What are you doing?
看风景
I was looking at a Vista.
没时间给你看风景
There’s no time for Vistas.
我们行程很紧
We’ve got a schedule!
我知道 但这里好舒服 还有靠垫
I know but it’s nice, comfy there’s cushions.
你看着就像在后台区休息
You look like you’re at some kind of backstage area at Latitude.
走吧
Come on.
好吧
Alright.
我刚刚看见乔·怀丽和北极猴子的团员在那儿
I’ve just seen Jo Whiley down there with one of the Arctic Monkeys.
你当然能看到
Course you have.
我要怎么下去 没有台阶啊
How am I gonna get down? Have you seen the step?!
在开启紧张的旅程前
Before we can begin to fling ourselves into the fray
咱们得赶紧买些东西
we need to make a pressing purchase.
我担心我的头会被晒伤
I’m worried about getting sunburn on my head.
好在罗马最古老的帽子店就在这儿
Yeah, luckily Rome’s oldest hat shop is here.
字幕
The cats at Antica Maniffattura Capelli
have been brutally pummelling high quality headgear for 80 years.
字幕
This is the classic Fedora hat.
Wow this is lovely.
字幕
This is a man who owns his own winery.
Cappelli’s is crammed with a shiz ton of wooden formers
字幕
meaning a dude can get his dome piece made to measure.
Would it be possible to change the ribbon, the band?
字幕
Thank you very much.
-Are you matching it to the tie?  -Yeah.
字幕
Nice.
Think I prefer the original ribbon- no I don’t its fine.
字幕
Like some kind of post-colonial Kojak reboot
we saunter through Rome and commence pointing at POIs
字幕
Where are we going?
We’re going on a Fiat tour.
字幕
Really?
Well in a Fiat we’re not just touring a variety of Fiats.
字幕
The original Fiat 500 is to Italy what the mini is to Britain;
an impractically small nostalgic car.
字幕
Quite noisy isn’t it?
Welcome to Rome, welcome on board the Fiat 500 cars!
字幕
Guide Alvise walkie-talkies us through the antiquities
while we focus on being facetious.
字幕
There are very relaxed driving conditions in Rome.
With an even longer look at the Colosseum earmarked
字幕
for the part that calls itself 2
we trundle towards former chariot racing venue the Circus Maximus.
字幕
Stadium for the chariot races, Ben- Hur to your right.
Oh Ben-Hur.
字幕
You need to back off the espressos.
And on the far side of the circus we managed
字幕
to record this terrific shot of the Palatine hill.
So to the right you can see Caesars Palace.
字幕
I’ve actually been to Caesars Palace,
I saw Elton John there do the million dollar piano
字幕
and I’m hoping to go back and see Celine Dion.
Well that will be lovely.
字幕
It would be nice
Then we rev on to the southernmost of Rome’s septet of summits:
字幕
the Avantine hill.
At its apex stands a priory belonging to The Knights of Malta
字幕
which has sovereign status, like an embassy!
Yes so welcome here, it is the only keyhole, in the world,
字幕
which you are allowed to peep through.
And through the keyhole you will see three countries in line,
字幕
here in Italy, the Island Malta and then we will have the Vatican.
It is very well framed.
字幕
With midday refusing to relent,
the ambient temp is pretty flipping far from mild.
字幕
I’ve lost use out of this eye.
All the sun creams gone in there.
字幕
I’m really weeping out of this,
it’s not because I find the conversation upsetting.
字幕
Oh you really are! I’ll give you a tissue.
It’s fine you don’t need both eyes to drive.
字幕
How do you think Nelson drove.
Thank you very much, I’ll just stick that in there.
字幕
That’s reassuring.
In another country.
字幕
On the other side of the road.
Hashtag Romebantz .
字幕
Our subsequent stop off serves
as a literalised metaphor of this show’s obsession with time.
字幕
So this is a tradition when the Pope was king
and he was annoyed with 900 churches,
字幕
900 bells ringing at different times at noon.
So he said hold the phone,
字幕
wait for my signal then you can ring the bells.
I would have loved it if he had said ‘hold the phone’ in 1850.
字幕
The Pope’s chosen signal was the soothing sound of cannon fire.
We’ve got the talking clock in England;
字幕
you can call up anytime you want.
And they’ve been blasting away every day for the last century and a half.
字幕
I’m going in.
That was loud, that was loud.
字幕
But that pumped up pistol
has provided a welcome punctuation point to our period of touring.
字幕
Well thank you for this tour, it’s been a pleasure.
I once saw a documentary on Rome and it reminds me of that.
字幕
It’s good to bring that memory so vividly to life.
We now opt to cop a closer scope at
字幕
perhaps the most Catholic city within a city on earth,
I’m talking the Vat to the I to the Can.
字幕
0.44 square kilometres,
smallest internationally recognised state in the world
字幕
, the Vatican! Nine miles of museums,
we’ve not got time for that.
字幕
So we’re not even going to go in.
What?!
字幕
Look at the queue! It’s ridiculous we can’t go in there.
Take it in then move on.
字幕
I would say if I had a dream,
it would be to stand outside the Vatican,
字幕
holding hands with one of my favourite comedians.
Just spontaneously, romantically holding-
字幕
Well I don’t think we can get Jim Davidson out here on such short notice.
Right.
字幕
Shall we?
Yeah.
字幕
Alright.
But to make sure we fully get our Pope on, we hit up a kiosk.
字幕
Hi, I don’t even know how to say this:
Do you have the Pope magazine?
字幕
Ahh oh fabulous ‘Il Mio Papa’
Pope Francis, he’s actually one of my favourite Popes.
字幕
Who’s your top five?
Okay, so err Pope Benedict, Pope John Paul, Pope John Paul II,
字幕
Pope Francis and I don’t know any other Popes.
Where are you going?
字幕
Oh do we just stand here?
Yes ideally.
字幕
Look at this- there’s the Pope whacking a kid.
Not very nice is it? How often does this come out do you know?
字幕
Every week.
Are you serious?!
字幕
Yeah, that’s him protecting himself against a female assailant.
Do you want this for your files?
字幕
No.
Okay.
字幕
As the sun sinks beneath the Tiber
we seek to explore the Italian soul via a colossal carve up.
字幕
You know this is a Michelin starred joint.
Is it? It’s wasted on me.
字幕
I have the eating age of a nine year old.
You mainly like plain crisps.
字幕
And fizzy pop.
Chef Riccard Di Giancinto’s five course menu
字幕
is a radical reimagining of the Italian classics,
and business opens with an amuse bouche of my old enemy - savoury macarons.
字幕
Would you ever cook like this at home?
Yeah frequently. No.
字幕
And the starters don’t stop.
See this Maritozzi bun and liquidised Carbonara for details.
字幕
No?
Don’t tell anyone but it’s very greasy.
字幕
As the courses continue,
we must now contend with the sheer scale of our tableware.
字幕
Richard you know what they say: When in Rome…
You managed to get that in finally.
字幕
Thank you.
Took a while.
字幕
It takes so long to reach- I was tipping it for about 2 hours!
I had to stop and take another breath.
字幕
It’s amazing!
I can’t get at it.
字幕
Eating with elegance, we plough through pasta…
Bosh. Lovely. What’s next?
字幕
On our way to the closer; a Roman oxtail
in the shape of one of Gulliver’s Personal Stash of Ferrero Rochers…
字幕
If I was a food critic-
yes.
字幕
Which in a sense you are.
-I would say it tastes nice.
字幕
Matt’s desert is a fruit and veg fusion of Celery strawberries and almonds
while I crunch down a quasi-conventional tiramisu.
字幕
I’ve wolfed that.
I have no class.
字幕
And I’ve very much enjoyed it.
Would you like to try some of this?
字幕
Of course I would.
This culinary crush ends with petit fours-
字幕
My Lord and Saviour what on earth is going on?
Lads, lads, lads, there’s so much food here.
字幕
I shall end up over weight.
… and a cup of joe.
字幕
If I were to rate this on Time Out best eats,
it’s a hard 5.
字幕
Out of what?
5.
字幕
Oh right.
How do you feel this went?
字幕
I think it was delicious.
I need to be asleep.
字幕
I need this coffee so I can get to the bed to fall asleep.
Now I’m awake.
字幕
So I might need some of this.
Still in the fist of our excess,
字幕
we stagger serenely t’wards our pre-day two doss down,
after which we’ll: Lob coins-
字幕
Bang.
Touch sticks-
字幕
That could have hurt!
And walk next to a person!
字幕
Friends, you re-join Matt Lucas and I,
the proprietor of this nasal lisp,
字幕
for the second segment of this ground-breaking minibreak in relic ridden Rome.
On Day 1 you may have already forgotten how: We revved…
字幕
Alright!
Recoiled…
字幕
That was loud.
And remained in character-
字幕
Bosh. Lovely. What’s next?
Day 2 starts crowd-beatingly early at one of Rome’s most notable nooks.
字幕
Yes! You do recognise it from the Lizzie McGuire movie.
It’s the same fountain, the Trevi fountain.
字幕
Oh right! Who’s Trevor?
It’s named after Trevor MacDonald.
字幕
Oh right.
Dispiritingly, we’re so early that
字幕
we hit the non-photogenic fountain cleaning slot,
but will it stop us from enacting an ancient coin toss? Let’s find out!
字幕
There’s a very strict tradition.
You have to throw with you your right hand over your left shoulder.
字幕
Legend has it that Roman Legionaries would throw three coins this way.
Bang.
字幕
I wished for a champions league place for Arsenal.
What does that mean exactly?
字幕
Dunno.
This ritual was supposed to ensure safe return to Rome
字幕
from far flung parts of the empire.
Save some for the wide shot.
字幕
Okay, ready? 3,2,1, no.
4,3,2,-3, 2, 1, but we’ll  do it on zero.
字幕
3,2,1, zero.
At 255 years old the Trevi fountain is the closest
字幕
that Rome comes to a new build.
Especially compared to this crate.
字幕
The Colosseum was built to provide free entertainment
and to re-enforce the might of Rome:
字幕
the same reason why I built my side-return.
Either she’s going through a legal document or she’s our tour guide.
字幕
Hi!
Hello
字幕
Nice to meet you, I’m Laura.
Tempus fugit, so let’s jointly take note of the top spec architecture,
字幕
pioneering use of concrete and multiple gates allowing easy access to approx.
65,000 bods before we glide inside…
字幕
We are entering the Colosseum from actually the loser gate.
The loser gate,
字幕
Exactly
Thank you.
字幕
Despite being well old, this heap still stands up to scrutiny.
Beneath the floor a network of lifts
字幕
provided access to the frankly sandy stage.
So we have in the morning hunting games until 12 o’clock.
字幕
And they stopped to do public execution here.
And then arrived the Gladiator in the evening.
字幕
It’s a bit grim isn’t it?
-You’re not pro the execution of hundreds of thousands of people.  -I’m not.
字幕
I’m actually not.
Well you need to start making that clear on your twitter feed.
字幕
On the plus side entry was gratis and there was complimentary nosebag.
They had free snacks;
字幕
Free snacks
Yeah, The Emperor would provide all this.
字幕
You see the illusion of generosity, but in reality, he was a (explicit)
Exactly!
字幕
Hey he provided chicken wings.
What have you ever done?
字幕
I have provided food for thirty or forty in my house;
I did not make them fight to the death.
字幕
With that that bare-faced lie still ringing round the arena,
we bid Laura bye and, perforce, bust.
字幕
Uncle Richard?
That’s right.
字幕
Where are we going?
I’ll tell you where we’re going, we’re going to overtake them,
字幕
then we are going to Tazza D’oro, cup of gold, for a granita de café.
Sugary expresso is frozen to a melting sorbet consistency
字幕
and topped off with whipped cream to create a caffeinated sundae.
Cheers.
字幕
There we go.
That’s what the Vikings would do.
字幕
And, near the end of my outstretched digit lies the set up to the following pun.
That’s very much in the pantheon of things
字幕
that you should look at whilst you’re here.
That’s correct.
字幕
Oh that’s quite strong.
I don’t usually have coffee so I might be bouncing off the walls.
字幕
Are you pleased you’ve seen the Pantheon from the outside?
Not bothered.
字幕
You’re unbelievable.
Don’t steal my angle.
字幕
Come on.
Overwhelmed by the pulchritude, we lope off to get physical-
字幕
That’s too short.
Oh I was gonna say erotic.
字幕
Okay.
Since 1999 this school has offered historically
字幕
accurate lessons in Gladiatorial combat.
Hi.
字幕
Hi, welcome to Gladiator School.
Today you will be training with my Medusa, the head of the Gladiators.
字幕
He’s the spitting image of my accountant.
Really?
字幕
And at the end of the training you will fight him with one of these.
Fight him?! Wow that’s heavy.
字幕
Ok, he has no idea of the fury inside me
that I’m going to unleash on him.
字幕
Perfect.
In this thrilling montage we show our progress through a series of warm ups
字幕
in which we display our agility and courage.
Did they have deodorant in Ancient Rome?
字幕
No.
Cause this would have stank! Imagine they did all of this pre Lynx!
字幕
Gladiators used short swords and, equipped with wooden facsimiles,
we learnt the moves to repel strikes to the head-
字幕
Head!
the neck-
字幕
Necks!
– still the neck–
字幕
Other side!
Haha, Frank Butcher!
字幕
legs-
Legs!
字幕
and the tum tum.
Stomach!
字幕
Finally, in a newly scored sub-arena of the arena, the combat intensifies.
Off you go Matt.
字幕
Head.
Err what was next? Leg! Stomach! Head again!
字幕
Richard
Round 2.
字幕
Yes round 2.
That’s my signature.
字幕
Fantastic.
He’s been tangoed.
字幕
Only one thing can top this adrenaline rush, and that’s ‘dot dot dot’…
And then a certificate do we?
字幕
Yes sure, you get a certificate.
Great they’ve dipped it in tea!
字幕
You will get a Latin name as well.
Your new name is Crixvs.
字幕
He’s the best friend of Spartacus.
Ah lovely, did he stand up for him though?
字幕
No he was crucified.
Ohhh.
字幕
Now Matt, your new name is Spartacus!
Hey.
字幕
He gets Spartacus and I get crucified Crixvs?!
He died first.
字幕
Spartacus gets top billing I mean there wasn’t Crixvs the movie.
Having sacked Rome for culture, history,
字幕
and cuisine it’s time to swipe some swag!
So we head to the Via Margutta, home to La Bottega del Marmoraro
字幕
where two generations of the Fiorentini Family
have carved marble tablets to order.
字幕
This place is ‘marbleous’
Haha, I do not understand English.
字幕
Armed only with a humble translation app on a smart phone,
we effortlessly enter into life-affirming dialogue
字幕
Thank you for having us visit your shop.
Tell me, please, why do you carve marble?
字幕
Whoa,whoa,whoa
Nepotism is the answer.
字幕
Because we did not want it,
because my dad did it, continues to do it.
字幕
We soon reach our modest data limit and are forced to put nib to pad.
That’s the date of birth and then I only need to-
字幕
cause that will save my estate.
And me…
字幕
Careful that’s an original.
So I want ‘Up the Gunners’ cause I’m an Arsenal fan.
字幕
Ok one hour.
One hour?!
字幕
That’s a tight turn around.
Okay thank you.
字幕
Ciao.
Once more we must rely on a Bafta-baiting montage
字幕
in order to compress this eternity.
Hello once more.
字幕
Right what you got?
‘Forza Gunners’ well that’s wonderful thank you very much.
字幕
I tell you what, I’m less happy, because, look,
there’s meant to be room here for the end date.
字幕
Not born 1977, died dot, dot, dot.
On the back.
字幕
On the back?! People have to walk round?!
Yes.
字幕
Where are you going to be buried?
Somewhere small.
字幕
There’s your thirty euros.
I think you are very difficult.
字幕
That would have been better just with the full stop.
He was born 1977, died.
字幕
Ciao.
Ciao, I’m sorry about my friend.
字幕
Ciao
A landscape headstone courtesy of the Italian David Crosby
字幕
completes a coin drop of 831 gbp per per.
And as a backdrop to our recap,
字幕
we select to the cultural and political epicentre of ancient Rome, the Forum.
Thought, reflections, assessments.
字幕
I enjoyed being in a Fiat
with someone who’s an even worse driver than I am.
字幕
How dare you! I’m very pleased with the hat purchase.
I, regret mine a little…
字幕
Why?
I fear if I was to wear this out shopping,
字幕
I might get one or two comments.
Like ‘nice hat-Where can I get one?’
字幕
You’ve had a nice time haven’t you?
It’s been a belter.
字幕
If I had to pick a favourite moment,
I’d say the moment the lasted two days,
字幕
in which I spent time with you and I got to know you a bit more.
Stop it.
字幕
So where are you going next?
Well ideally, departures.
字幕
Right.
Cars running.
字幕
Lovely.
Do you want to sit in the front you get car sick.
字幕
I get travel sick- this whole things a disaster.